{"tossups": [{"question": "This body of water is home to ruins linked with the Tiwanaku [[tee-wah-NAH-koo]] people, who possibly built a massive, now-ruined temple on the Isla de la Luna. Thor Heyerdahl's <em>Ra II</em> [[TWO]] was constructed by the reed craftsmen from Suriki in this lake. The first warship to navigate this lake was the gunboat <em>Colo Colo</em>, sent by Chile to threaten two other countries during the War of the Pacific. For the point, name this \"highest navigable lake\" in the world, lying between Peru and Bolivia.", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Titicaca</u></b> (or Lago <b><u>Titicaca</u></b>; accept <b><u>Titiqaqa</u></b> Qucha)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In this election year, a candidate won 500 electoral votes for the first time. William Lemke attempted to run a third-party \"Union\" ticket with the backing of radio priest Charles Coughlin, though he failed to win a single state. Vermont and Maine were the sole states to vote Republican in this election cycle, which saw Texan John Nance Garner win his second and final term as vice president. For the point, give this election year in which Franklin D. Roosevelt won his second of four presidential victories.", "answer": "<b><u>1936</u></b> United States presidential election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A last ditch effort to save the Western Roman Empire led to the Cape Bon Expedition against these people, which was successfully repelled by Genseric's deployments of fire ships. Due to their Arian beliefs, Justinian sent Belisarius to subdue these people. Under the rule of Gelimer, these people were routed at the Battle of Tricamerum, twenty miles from Carthage. The earlier 455 sack of Rome was conducted by, for the point, what Germanic people whose name became synonymous with \"looting\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Vandal</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Vandal</u></b>ic People)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "John Gast painted an angelic woman representing this specific concept towing telegraph wires while a tribe of Native Americans flee. A political cartoon advocating this position depicts an eagle below the words \"Ten Thousand Miles from Tip to Tip.\" Proponents of this ideological position led the \"All of Mexico Movement\" during the Mexican-American War. Aiming to \"civilize\" the West, for the point, what 19th-century American cultural belief held that the United States should control all of North America?", "answer": "<b><u>Manifest Destiny</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>American Progress</u></b></em>; prompt on \"American Exceptionalism\"; prompt on answer which imply the \"US is expanding\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "\"Circling over Shannon\" became a euphuism for inebriation in Ireland following an incident where this politician's drunkenness led to his failure to meet with Prime Minister Albert Reynolds. This figure put down the Communist August Coup perpetrated by the Gang of Eight, while his economic liberalization led to the rise of the oligarchs like Mikhail Friedman. Vladimir Putin was the handpicked successor of, for the point, which first president of the Russian Federation?", "answer": "Boris <b><u>Yeltsin</u></b> (or Boris Nikolayevich <b><u>Yeltsin</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man executed his first wife, Lady Tsukiyama [[soo-kee-YAH-mah]], following her conspiracy to marry her son off to the daughter of a rival warlord. The Okamoto Daihachi [[\"die\"-HAH-chee]] incident led to this man's persecution of his Christian subjects. This former vassal of Oda Nobunaga [[NOH-boo-NAH-gah]] became the last \"Great Unifier\" of Japan following the Battle of Sekigahara [[SEH-kee-guh-HAH-rah]]. For the point, name this warlord who established a namesake Shogunate in 1603.", "answer": "<b><u>Tokugawa</u></b> Ieyasu (accept <b><u>Matsudaira</u></b> Takechiyo; or <b><u>Matsudaira</u></b> Jir\u014dsabur\u014d Motonobu; or <b><u>Matsudaira</u></b> Kurandonosuke Motoyasu; or <b><u>Matsudaira</u></b> Ieyasu; accept <b><u>T\u014dsh\u014d</u></b> <b><u>Daigongen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A conference on the Brijuni [[bree-YOO-nee]] Islands between John Foster Dulles and this nation's leader kept it from joining the Eastern Bloc. This country's Communists defeated the Chetniks and Usta\u0161e [[oo-STAH-shuh]] during World War Two under that leader, who became a founder of the Non-Aligned Movement. Led for nearly forty years by Josip Broz Tito, for the point, what was this country that ruled over the territory of modern-day nations like Serbia, Croatia, and Slovenia?", "answer": "Socialist Federal Republic of <b><u>Yugoslavia</u></b> (accept Socijalisti\u010dka Federativna Republika <b><u>Jugoslavija</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "When this man learned his future victim would be attending a performance of <em>Still</em> <em>Waters Run Deep</em>, this man and his team, including Lewis Powell and David Herold, hoped to kidnap their targets en route. While hiding in the barn of Richard H. Garrett, this man was shot and killed by Boston Corbett. Shouting \"Sic Semper Tyrannus\" after committing his most famous deed, for the point, who was this assassin of Abraham Lincoln?", "answer": "John Wilkes <b><u>Booth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While in Parliament, this man helped draft the Root and Branch Bill meant to abolish episcopal governance. This politician from Huntingdon served under Thomas Fairfax in one army, and led the massacre of Irish civilians at Drogheda [[DRAW-hed-duh]]. This man, who dismissed the Rump Parliament, was one of the signatories of Charles I's death warrant. For the point, name this Lord Protector who dominated English politics following the English Civil War.", "answer": "Oliver <b><u>Cromwell</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A monarch of this house known as \"Thulaim,\" or the Host, began a war with a southern neighbor in an effort to bring the Emirate of Asir into its sphere of influence. The Sudairi Seven are a faction within this family who have controlled the crown since the 1980s. The title Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques was taken by a king of this dynasty named Faisal. An Arabian kingdom is named for, for the point, what royal house which is effectively led by Mohammed bin Salman?", "answer": "House of <b><u>Saud</u></b> (accept <b><u>Saud</u></b>i Arabia)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A David Belasco play, <em>The Girl of the Golden West</em> inspired one of this man's operas, which sees Dick Johnson and Minnie flee California during the Gold Rush. After receiving a music box from the Boxer Rebellion, this man incorporated real Chinese folk songs into an opera that includes the aria \"Nessun Dorma.\" For the point, name this Italian composer of <em>Turandot</em> who also depicted the American presence in Japan in his opera <em>Madame Butterfly</em>.", "answer": "Giacomo <b><u>Puccini</u></b> (or Giacomo Antonio Domenico Michele Secondo Maria <b><u>Puccini</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "The Apadana hoard included one of these items with a sea turtle imprinted in it, the Aegina stater. The earliest proto-form of these items were found in a tomb in Anyang and consist of bronze replicas of cowrie shells. Sacred animals were often printed on these items, which were first cast in their recognizable form in the Kingdom of Lydia. Several gold versions of these items depict Darius the Great. For the point, name these round metal objects used by many ancient realms as currency.", "answer": "<b><u>Coins</u></b> (accept specific coins such as the <b><u>Tong Bei</u></b>; or <b><u>Croesid</u></b>; or <b><u>Daric</u></b>; or <b><u>Siglos</u></b>; or <b><u>Stater</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Salvador Laurel became vice president of this country in the aftermath of a disputed 1986 election. That election led to the EDSA Revolution in this country, which brought Corazon Aquino [[ah-KEE-noh]] to power. Her husband Ninoy was supposedly killed on the orders of a dictator of this country, whose wife owned 3,000 pairs of shoes. Ferdinand Marcos was the dictator of, for the point, what country, where he ruled from Manila?", "answer": "Republic of the <b><u>Philippines</u></b> (accept Republika ng <b><u>Pilipinas</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Though it's not Sparta, this city's nobility were the Spartoi, or \"sown-men,\" created by this city's mythical founder, Cadmus. Several Argive champions died supporting Polynices [[PAH-lee-NYE-seez]] as the \"Seven Against\" [this city], though their sons eventually installed Thersander as ruler. Creon was a mythical ruler of, for the point, what Ancient Greek city state that witnessed the tragedy of Oedipus?", "answer": "<b><u>Thebes</u></b> (accept <b><u>Thebai</u></b>; or <b><u>Thiva</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The Count of Vergennes [[VER-jens]] attempted to negotiate an early version of this treaty that would give an \"Indian Barrier State\" to Spanish control. The final version of this treaty granted fishing rights off the Grand Banks to one party, who sent Henry Laurens and John Jay, among others, as negotiators. Ratified in Annapolis, for the point, what treaty offered property restitution to Loyalists in order to end the American Revolutionary War?", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>Paris</u></b>, 1783", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A confederacy of sovereign states of this faith were known as the Misls [[MEE-suls]]. The Dal Khalsa army served this faith, which destroyed the Durrani Empire of Afghanistan after capturing Lahore. An empire named for this religion fought two successive wars with the British, leading to its dissolution into four provinces, including Punjab. For the point, name this militaristic Indian religion that was founded by Guru Nanak.", "answer": "<b><u>Sikh</u></b>ism (accept <b><u>Sikh</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's childhood mentor Sim\u00f3n Rodr\u00edguez introduced him to Enlightenment ideas like liberty and human rights. In 1812, this man issued the Cartagena [[kar-tah-HEH-nah]] Manifesto, detailing why he believed the First Republic had failed. At the end of his Admirable Campaign in 1813, this man marched into Caracas [[kah-RAH-kahss]] but later was forced to flee to Jamaica. For the point, name this man who served as president of Gran Colombia from 1819 to 1830 and was known as \"The Liberator.\"", "answer": "Sim\u00f3n <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b> (or Sim\u00f3n Jos\u00e9 Antonio de la Sant\u00edsima Trinidad <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b> y Ponte Palacios y Blanco)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The American Federation of Labor criticized the time that elapsed between this group's trial and the alleged crime at the Slater and Morrill Shoe Company. These people were convicted by Webster Thayer of first-degree murder and died via electric chair at Charlestown State Prison. In 1977, Michael Dukakis officially declared that this pair was tried unfairly. For the point, name this pair of Italian immigrants accused of murdering a guard and paymaster during a 1920 armed robbery.", "answer": "Niccolo <b><u>Sacco</u></b> and Bartolomeo <b><u>Vanzetti</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Algeciras [[AL-jeh-SEE-rahs]] Conference resolved a diplomatic incident in this country. Abd el-Krim led anti-colonial resistance in this country during the Rif War. A \"crisis\" in this country polarized relations between France and German in the lead-up to World War One, after which an international zone was created in this country's city of Tangier. For the point, name this North African kingdom across the Strait of Gibraltar from Spain.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Morocco</u></b> or al-Mamlakah <b><u>al-Maghribiyyah</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Early settlers from these people destroyed an Osage village in the Claremore Mound Massacre. This people\u2019s sovereignty was affirmed in the case <em>Worcester</em> [[WUR-STUR]] <em>v.</em> <em>Georgia</em>, and their writing system was developed by Sequoyah. These people were rounded up by Winfield Scott after a small group signed the Treaty of New Echota on their behalf. For the point, name this Native American tribe which made up the majority of the dead on the Trail of Tears.", "answer": "<b><u>Cherokee</u></b> (or the <b><u>Cherokee</u></b> Nation; accept <b><u>Anigiduwagi</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tsalagi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The fifth ruler of this name, who was described as the \"precursor to the antichrist\" by Theophanes [[thee-AH-fah-nees]], created a standing, professional army known as the <em>themata</em> [[theh-MAH-tah]]. The eleventh ruler of this name, known as \"Palaiologos\" [[pah-lye-oh-LOH-goss]], shed his armor and died battling the Ottoman army of Mehmed [[MEKH-med]] during a 1453 siege. The legalization of Christianity was done by the first Roman emperor with, for the point, which Latin name?", "answer": "<b><u>Constantine</u></b> (accept <b><u>Constantinus</u></b> in place of \"Constantine\"; accept <b><u>Constantine</u> </b>I; accept <b><u>Constantine</u></b> the Great; accept <b><u>Constantine</u></b> V; accept <b><u>Constantine</u></b> XI)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During his time in the military, this man was almost killed in a fire aboard the USS <em>Forrestal</em>. In 2002, this man co-authored a campaign reform bill with Russ Feingold. After returning to the Senate in 2017 following treatment for a brain tumor, this man gave a dramatic thumbs down on a vote to repeal Obamacare, following that with a speech against party-line voting. For the point, name this losing Republican of the Election of 2008 and Arizona senator who died in 2018.", "answer": "John <b><u>McCain</u></b> (or John Sidney <b><u>McCain</u></b> III)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Some major pieces of legislation passed during this man\u2019s political tenure, including the Factories Act and the Holidays with Pay Act. This man failed to prevent the German invasion of Norway, which prompted the Norway Debate in the British House of Commons. Shortly afterward, this man resigned as prime minister but remained as leader of the Conservative Party. For the point, name this politician who was succeeded as Prime Minister by Winston Churchill.", "answer": "Neville <b><u>Chamberlain</u></b> (or Arthur Neville <b><u>Chamberlain</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An artwork made from this material known as <em>The Dancing Girl</em> and found in the city of Mohenjo-Daro was known as the \"Mona Lisa\" of the Indus River Civilization. <em>The Dying</em> <em>Gladiator</em> is a Roman copy of a Greek statue believed to have been originally sculpted from this material. The first freestanding nude of the Renaissance period, Donatello's <em>David</em>, was produced from this metal alloy. For the point, name this material, commonly used in artwork, an alloy of tin and copper.", "answer": "<b><u>Bronze</u></b> (or <b><u>Bronze</u></b> sculpture)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This weapon is known to Mexican drug cartel members as \"El Cuerno de Chivo,\" or the \"Goat's Horn,\" due to the shape of its magazines. One of these weapons is depicted on the official Coat of Arms of Zimbabwe, forming an \"X\" shape with a spade. One of these weapons appears on the flag of Mozambique, making it the only modern armament to appear on a nation's ensign. For the point, name this popular assault rifle, designed by Mikhail Kalashnikov, used by the Soviet Army for much of the twentieth century.", "answer": "<b><u>AK</u></b>-47 (or <b><u>A</u></b>vtomat <b><u>K</u></b>alashnikova; accept <b><u>Kalishnikov</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on more generic answers like \"Rifle\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader was opposed by the <em>Pieds-Noirs</em> [[PYEHD NWAHR]] for granting independence to Algeria through the <em>Evian</em> Accords. In 1968, this man fled Paris during student protests, and after a 1940 military defeat, this exiled man delivered the Appeal of 18 June against the Vichy [[VEE-shee]] regime. This man led the Provisional French Government during the Liberation from Nazi rule and founded the Fifth Republic. For the point, name this leader of Free France during World War Two.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>de Gaulle</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1981, Lynn Margulis published a book explaining the endo-symbiotic theory of the origin of these things. In 1855, Rudolf Virchow [[FEER-koh]] showed that new examples of these units are formed from a type of division. These biological entities were discovered in 1665 in cork samples by Robert Hooke using an early compound microscope. For the point, name these long-studied basic structural units of living organisms.", "answer": "<b><u>Cell</u></b> (accept specific types of <b><u>Cell</u></b>s like Plant <b><u>Cell</u></b>s or Cork <b><u>Cell</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Using the pseudonym \"Frank Talk,\" Steve Biko [[BEE-koh]] wrote articles opposing this policy. A precursor to this policy known as the Native Lands Act created a series of reserves for minorities like the Venda and Xhosa [[KOH-sah]]. Prime Minister D.F. Malan is considered the architect of this policy, and ANC members like Thabo Mbeki [[em-BEH-kee]] and Nelson Mandela opposed this policy. For the point, name this 20th century South African policy of \"separateness.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Apartheid</u></b> (prompt on descriptions like \"South African segregation\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "While serving as head of the Naval Consulting Board during World War One, this man sought to discover a domestic source of rubber. Another of this man's ventures was the first film studio, \"Black Maria,\" and he produced films like <em>Electrocuting an Elephant</em> and <em>The</em> <em>Great Train Robbery</em>. Often called \u201cthe Wizard of Menlo Park,\u201d for the point, who was this prolific inventor with 1,093 patents, including one for the light bulb?", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Edison</u></b> (or Thomas Alva <b><u>Edison</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This park's 50 square mile \"Zone of Death\" is a region where you can theoretically get away with murder in legal scholar Brian Kalt's thought experiment. Frank Jay Haynes became the official photographer of this park, recording the first visit to it by a sitting President after Rutherford B. Hayes travelled there while fighting poor health. The Washburn Expedition of 1870 explored this parks Upper and Lower Geyser Basin, naming the largest one \"Old Faithful.\" The oldest national park in the US is, for the point, which reserve which lies in Wyoming, Idaho, and Montana?", "answer": "<b><u>Yellowstone</u></b> National Park", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The location of this battle was codenamed by one side as \"A-F\", although some thought the real target was the Aleutian Islands. \"Nagumo's Dilemma\" occurred during this battle, in which a commander refused to commit to a risky attack on Task Force 16. The Japanese began this battle as part of the \"barrier strategy\" in response to Doolittle's Raid on Tokyo. For the point, identify this decisive 1942 battle in which U.S. forces sunk four Japanese carriers at the cost of the USS <em>Yorktown</em>.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Midway</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these animals named Jack served as the dedicated assistant to a disabled railway signalman in the Cape Province. One of these animals dressed in a French uniform was legendarily hanged by the citizens of Hartlepool after it was the sole survivor of a Napoleonic-era naval battle. A trial named for this animal concerned John Scopes' teaching of evolution in a Tennessee public school. For the point, name these primates split into \"Old World\" and \"New World\" varieties, the former lacking a tail.", "answer": "<b><u>Monkey</u></b> (prompt on \"Primate\" before mentioned; accept Scopes <b><u>Monkey</u></b> Trial; accept <b><u>Baboon</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A scandal named for this project saw French politicians take bribes from engineers, including Gustave [[goo-STAHV]] Eiffel. Walter Reed conducted research into the causes of yellow fever during the construction of this project, which was finished thanks to a rebellion sponsored by Theodore Roosevelt. In 1979, the Carter administration agreed to hand this structure over to its namesake country at a future date. For the point, name this structure that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.", "answer": "<b><u>Panama Canal</u></b> (accept <b><u>Canal de Panam\u00e1</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one work set during this war, the surgeon Rinaldi introduces the main character to the nurse Catherine Barkley. Frederic Henry serves as an ambulance driver during this war in a novel which earned the ire of the Italian government for its depiction of the Battle of Caporetto. For the point, name this war which serves as the setting of Ernest Hemingway's <em>A Farewell to Arms</em> and created the \u201clost generation.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>World</u></b> War <b><u>One</u></b> (accept <b><u>First World</u></b> War; accept the <b><u>Great</u></b> War; accept <b><u>WW</u></b> <b><u>One</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "In the American South, the Ku Klux Klan openly burned this group's album following their frontman's comment that \"[this band] was bigger than Jesus.\" Over thirty percent of the U.S. viewed this rock group's appearance on the Ed Sullivan Show, fueling a namesake \"Mania\" in America. George Harrison, Ringo Starr, Paul McCartney, and John Lennon made up, for the point, which highly-influential British band of the 1960s?", "answer": "The <b><u>Beatles</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In November of 2021, Fruit of Islam member Norman Butler was exonerated for the assassination of this man after a 22-month investigation. This Black activist stated \"Our forefathers weren't the Pilgrims. We didn't land on Plymouth Rock; the rock was landed on us\" in the \"Ballot or the Bullet\" speech. A <em>hajj</em> to Mecca led this man to change his name to Malik el-Shabazz. For the point, name this black empowerment activist often at odds with Martin Luther King Jr.", "answer": "<b><u>Malcolm X</u></b> (accept Malcolm <b><u>Little</u></b>; accept <b><u>Malik el-Shabazz</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}